Harry F. Brown Papers
© 2003 University of Connecticut
Harry F. Brown Papers.
1908-1933, 1959, 1964.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center
Brown, Harry F. (1886-1980)
3.25 linear feet.
The Harry F. Brown Papers consist of 478 photographic images in various media of railroad electrification equipment along electrified main line section of the Shoreline route of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.
MSS20020105
Biography
Harry Farnsworth Brown was born in New Haven, Connecticut, on August 17, 1886, the son of Harry Bushnell Brown and Annie Josephine Burdick. He was educated in the New Haven public schools and attended Yale University from 1903-1907, where he graduated from the Sheffield Scientific School. Following graduation he was employed by General Electric Company.
In 1910 he took a position in the Electrical Engineering Department of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. He served as a draftsman (1910), assistant engineer (1911-1922), assistant electrical engineer (1922-1946), and electrical engineer (1946-1952). When he left the railroad in 1952 he was Chief Engineer of the Engineering Department. From 1951 until his retirement he worked as a railroad consultant with Westinghouse International Co., and Gibbs & Hill in New York, New York.
Harry F. Brown married Grace A. Durham on October 11, 1911. They had six children. He was a lifelong member of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers. He died on August 11, 1980.
Scope and Content
The Harry F. Brown papers are composed of 478 images on glass plate negatives, photographic prints, flexible negatives, 35mm film, and 35mm mounted slides. The majority of the images were taken between 1908 and 1933, with a few from 1959 and 1964. Most of the images contain railroad electrification equipment, and specifically anchor bridges and catenary along the shoreline route of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. Precisely numbered anchor bridges with exact locations appear in the photographic prints and the 35mm slides.
There are also groups of other types of images within the collection. The flexible negatives contain interior and exterior images of the power plants at Cos Cob, Connecticut and New Haven, Connecticut, as well as at Nantasket, Massachusetts. Both the glass plate negatives and the flexible negatives depict the construction of catenary. The flexible images show the Milford Bridge under construction. The 35mm slides contain a series of images of the wreck of the Federal in Bridgeport, Connecticut, in July 1955, as well as images of multiple unit passenger cars. Finally, the slides also contain images of equipment sold to the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad by Goodrum Substation near Porter, Indiana.
The collection includes several noteworthy images. The glass plate negatives include an image of a model of an electrification system and an electrified railroad car on a table. The photographic prints contain two images of a fire on the railroad tracks. Finally, there are a few images throughout the collection of catenary wires being built by workmen with horses and buggies.
Special thanks to Michael Ribuffo of East Northport, New York, for his valuable assistance in revising and refining the descriptions of several of the images in 2004.
Organization
Series I: Glass plate negatives ( n.d, 1916-1917, 1921-1922 ) includes 9 inch x 7 inch and 4 inch x 4.5 inch negatives of both outdoor and indoor railroad electrification equipment in locations that include New Rochelle, New York, Bridgeport, Connecticut and New Haven, Connecticut. Examples of electrification equipment include, anchor bridges, catenary wires, drawbridge catenaries, right of ways, switch generators, telephone switchboards, transformers, and triangular catenaries.
Series II: Photographic prints (Black and White) ( n.d., 1930, 1931 ) includes 5 inch x 4 inch and 3.5 inch x 4.5 inch prints of railroad electrification equipment. Examples of equipment include anchor bridges on both the Harlem River Branch and the Main Line, catenary wires, railroad signals, transformers, and triangular catenary wires. Images were taken in the Bronx, New York, Oak Point, New York and Port Chester, New York. Also included are Bridgeport,Connecticut, Cedar Hill,Connecticut, Cos Cob,Connecticut, Darien, Connecticut, Devon,Connecticut, Greens Farms, Connecticut, Greenwich, Connecticut, New Haven, Connecticut, Sound Beach, Connecticut, South Norwalk, Connecticut, Stamford, Connecticut and Westport, Connecticut.
Series III: Flexible negatives ( n.d., 1908, 1912-1914, 1919-1921, 1930-1931, 1933 ) includes 9 inch x 7 inch saftey negatives, and 4.5 inch x 3.5 inch nitrate negatives of railroad electrification equipment. Images of the Cos Cob, Connecticut power plant, New Haven, Connecticut heat plant, and the Nantasket, Massachusetts power station are included among images of catenary construction and the construction of the Milford Bridge in Milford, Connecticut. Also included are images of equipment, such as anchor bridges, catenaries, circuit breakers, electric switch generators, lightening arresters, right of ways, rotaries, signal stations, switchboards, and triangular catenary wires. Images were taken at locations that include, Cos Cob, Connecticut, New Haven, Connecticut, and South Norwich, Connecticut; Nantasket, Massachusetts; and Porter, Indiana.
Series IV: 35mm developed film ( n.d. ) includes two rolls of black and white film with images of electrification equipment, including anchor bridges, catenary wires railroad bridges, and transformers.
Series V: 35mm mounted slides ( n.d., 1959, 1964 ) includes black and white and color images of railroad electrification equipment and a series of images of an unidentified train wreck. Electrification equipment images include anchor bridges on both the Harlem River Branch and the Main Line, busses, catenary wires, multiple unit passenger cars, pantographs, railroad traffic lights, signal towers, signal transfers, transformers, and triangular catenaries. The images were taken in locations that include, New Rochelle, New York; and Bridgeport, Connecticut, Danbury, Connecticut, and Stamford, Connecticut.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. See especially the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Records and related collections. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format, size and photographer's identification number.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Organizations:
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad; Boston and Maine Railroad; New York, Westchester & Boston Railway; Pennsylvania Railroad
Places:
Bridgeport, Connecticut; Cedar Hill, Connecticut; Cos Cob, Connecticut; Danbury, Connecticut; Darien, Connecticut; Devon, Connecticut; Greens Farms, Connecticut; Greenwich, Connecticut; Milford, Connecticut; New Haven, Connecticut; Sound Beach, Connecticut; South Norwalk, Connecticut; Stamford, Connecticut; Westport, Connecticut; Woodmont, Connecticut; Porter, Indiana; Nantasket, Massachusetts; Bronx, New York; New Rochelle, New York; Oak Point, New York; Port Chester, New York; West Farms, New York; South Mount Vernon, New York; Providence, Rhode Island
Subjects:
Railroads--Employees.; Railroads--Electrification.; Railroads--New England--Electrification.; Railroads--New England.
Document Types:
Photographs.; Negatives.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Diane Brown in September 2002.
Detailed Description/Box and Folder Listing
- Series I: Glass Plate Negatives, n.d., 1916-1917, 1921-1922
  - Subseries A: 9 inch X 7 inch, n.d., 1921-1922
    - Catenary wire and anchor brige stretching over railroad track, n.d. (Box 1:1)
    - Generators at the Cos Cob Power Plant, Cos Cob, Connecticut, n.d. (Box 1:2)
    - Transformers at the Cos Cob Power Plant, Cos Cob, Connecticut, n.d. (Box 1:3)
    - 22 KV oil circuit-breakers in switch house, n.d. (Box 1:4)
    - Workmen building an anchor bridge for catenary wires, including twelve workmen watching a crane lift a piece of the anchor bridge and New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad car 75953, n.d. (Box 1:5)
    - Workmen building an anchor bridge for catenary wires. Twelve men watch as a crane lifts a piece of the anchor bridge, which holds another workman. New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad car 75953 is also included in the image, n.d. (Box 1:6)
    - Sweeping view of partically constructed catenary bridges. Towers are in place but bridges are not yet installed, east of Stamford, Connecticut, ca. 1913 (Box 1:7)
    - Anchor bridge over a railroad track carrying catenary wires. Debris lies next to the track and two men stand on the track in the right bottom corner of the image, New Rochelle Junction, New York, n.d. (Box 1:8)
    - Anchor bridge over a railroad track with a man bending over in the left bottom corner of the image, New Rochelle Junction, New York, n.d. (Box 1:9)
    - Signal station 12 (SS12) at entrance to Westchester Yard, Harlem River Branch, ca. 1909 (Box 1:10)
    - Anchor bridge with catenary wires, Harlem River Branch, n.d. (Box 1:11)
    - View looking south of Signal Station tower 8 and junction of 4-track New York, Westchester & Boston Railway with 6-track Harlem River Branch of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, ca. 1912 (Box 1:12)
    - View looking north of Signal Station tower 8 and junction of 4-track New York, Westchester & Boston Railway with 6-track Harlem River Branch of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, ca. 1912 (Box 1:13)
    - Anchor bridge carrying catenary wires over railroad tracks. On the right side of the image a train approaches. A man stands on the right side of the railroad tracks, n.d. (Box 1:14)
    - An anchor bridge carrying catenary wires over railroad tracks. A Boston and Maine Railroad train with four visible cars, the most visible of which is car number 47427, stands on the left side of the image, n.d. (Box 1:15)
    - Anchor bridge carrying catenary wires over a railroad track. Small railroad buildings stand on each side of the track. A bridge stands in the background. Several anchor bridges are visible in the background, n.d. (Box 1:16)
    - Anchor bridge carrying catenary wires over railroad tracks. A bridge stands behind the anchor bridge and a large building stands to the left above the railroad tracks, n.d. (Box 1:17)
    - New York, Westchester & Boston Railway signal station at unknown location, possibly Pelham Parkway, n.d. (Box 1:18)
    - Model of an electrified train car and an electrification system stretched across three tables. The surrounding room contains plaques above a black board advertising possible lectures relating to the electrification of the railroad, n.d. (Box 1:19)
    - Drawbridge catenary over railroad tracks. A small railroad building stands on the left side of the tracks in the background, n.d. (Box 1:20)
    - Another view of a drawbridge catenary over railroad tracks, n.d. (Box 1:21)
    - Anchor bridge 633 at Signal Station 53, Greens Farms, Connecticut, n.d. (Box 1:22)
    - Catenary bridge 634 connected to switch house at Signal Station 53, Greens Farms, Connecticut, n.d. (Box 1:23)
    - Between South Mount Vernon, New York, and New Rochelle, New York, one post of anchor bridge G 34 connects to a small shed on the side of the railroad tracks. In the background stands a house and farm buildings, n.d. (Box 1:24)
    - A telephone switchboard mounted on a brick wall, n.d. (Box 1:25)
    - A telephone switchboard connected to a large wall of equipment on the bottom floor of a two-story room, n.d. (Box 1:26)
    - Unknown items, possibly sections of railroad ties, n.d. (Box 1:27)
    - Transformers at West Farms, New York located at the junction of the Harlem River division of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and the Westchester & Boston Railroad, at 174th Street in the Bronx. "Feeder" cables to West Farms from the Sherman Creek (201st Street in Manhattan) generating plant terminated at tranformers located on an out-door platform, one such transformer appearing in the photo., n.d. (Box 1:28)
    - Electrical wires attached to the underside of a bridge. A door leads into the stone wall of the bridge., n.d. (Box 1:29)
    - Electrical wires attched to the bottom side of a bridge, n.d. (Box 1:30)
    - Signal Station 78 in cut just east of New Haven, Connecticut, station, n.d. (Box 1:31)
    - An outside wall of a two-story building, the bottom story of which is brick and the top of which is wood. The window in the bottom story is boarded up. Another building is in the background on the left side of the image, n.d. (Box 1:32)
    - An unidentified roundhouse; railroad track terminates in the bottom right corner, n.d. (Box 1:33)
    - Another view of the same roundhouse wall, n.d. (Box 1:34)
    - A view of a different wall on the roundhouse. This section of the building is more square. A pile of blocks are on the ground in front of the building, n.d. (Box 1:35)
    - Another view of the square section of the roundhouse, n.d. (Box 1:36)
    - Electrical switch generator. This glass plate negative is broken and has been taped together by the previous owner, 1921 (Box 1:37)
    - Electrical switch generator, 1921 (Box 1:38)
    - A section of an electrical switch generator's equipment, 1921 (Box 1:39)
    - Another view of electrical switch generator equipment, 1921 (Box 1:40)
    - A different view of electrical switch generator equipment, 1921 (Box 1:41)
    - Electrical right of way between New Haven, Connecticut and Bridgeport Connecticut. The image includes buildings lining the railroad track on both sides as well as anchor bridges and catenary wires, 1922 (Box 1:42)
    - View of the right of way between New Haven, Connecticut and Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1922 (Box 1:43)
    - Tracks curving around a building, possibly behind the roundhouse in the railroad yard in New Haven, Connecticut, 1922 (Box 1:44)
    - In the cut west of the Mount Vernon, New York, railroad station, n.d. (Box 1:45)
    - In the cut west of the Mount Vernon, New York, railroad station, n.d. (Box 1:46)
    - Switch gear, n.d. (Box 1:47)
  - Subseries B: 4 inch X 4.5 inch, n.d., 1916-1917
    - Electric right of way. The image includes railroad tracks and multiple bridges that run parallel to and cross over them, n.d. (Box 2:48)
    - Electric right of way. The image includes railroad tracks, an anchor bridge, and buildings that stand parallel to and above the tracks, n.d. (Box 2:49)
    - Electric right of way in an unknown town. Railroad tracks run near small business buildings and a street, on which is a horse, carriage, and a person walking, n.d. (Box 2:50)
    - Providence, Warren & Bristol section electrified tracks at Providence, Rhode Island, terminal and tunnel through College Hill to East Providence, n.d. (Box 2:51)
    - Providence, Warren & Bristol section electrified tracks at Providence, Rhode Island, terminal and tunnel through College Hill to East Providence, n.d. (Box 2:52)
    - Four men working on railroad tracks with an anchor bridge above their heads. A railroad car is on the tracks in the background on the right and a small railroad building is on the left of the tracks next to the workmen, June 6, 1916 (Box 2:53)
    - A view of a triangular catenary over a railroad track including a railroad car, Stamford, Connecticut, June 6, 1916 (Box 2:54)
    - An image including a railroad bridge that spans a large body of water and a drawbridge catenary, June 6, 1916 (Box 2:55)
    - Triangle catenary over a railroad track, June 29, 1916 (Box 2:56)
    - A railroad right of way that appears to lead towards a building that is under construction. There are nine workman on the ground in front of the building and on its roof, n.d. (Box 2:57)
    - A railroad right of way with four people standing on the tracks, possibly on the east end of the New Haven, Connecticut, station, February, 1917 (Box 2:58)
- Series II: Photographic Prints (Black & White), n.d., 1930, 1931
  - Subseries A: 3.5 inch X 4.5 inch,1930, 1931
    - Railroad yard in New York state looking west. Three anchor bridges, including 2H on the Harlem River Branch, and several catenaries are visible, as well as one railroad car on the far left side and two in the right background,June, 1931 (Box 3:59)
    - Railroad signals in Oak Point, New York, looking east. Catenary wires and anchor bridges, including 41H on the Harlem River Branch, are included,December, 1930 (Box 3:60)
    - Railroad tracks in Oak Point, New York, (Bungay Street), looking west. A signal station is on the left and in the center are catenary wires and anchor bridges, including 42H on the Harlem River Branch,December 1930 (Box 3:61)
    - Transformer yard in Oak Point, New York, (Bungay Street) looking east. This is the same location as the previous photo (61) and contains the same signal station as well as anchor bridge 42H on the Harlem River Branch,December 1930 (Box 3:62)
    - Anchor bridge 58H on the Harlem River Branch with electrical equipment and catenary wires looking west in Oak Point, New York,December 1930 (Box 3:63)
    - Anchor bridge 58H on the Harlem River Branch with electrical equipment and catenary wires looking east in Oak Point, New York. This image was taken in the same location as the previous photo (63),December 1930 (Box 3:64)
    - Transformer yard in Oak Point, New York, looking east. This photo was taken in the same location as the previous two photos (63 and 64),December 1930 (Box 3:65)
    - South half of a transformer yard in Oak Point, New York, looking west. This photo was also taken in the same location as photos 63-65,December 1930 (Box 3:66)
    - View looking west from anchor bridge 245 at Signal Station 27 (Byram multiple-unit car yard) toward the Life Savers factory in Port Chester, New York, April 1931 (Box 3:67)
    - View looking east from anchor bridge 245 toward interlocking tower Signal Station 27, controlling entrance to Byram multiple-unit car yard, in Port Chester, New York, April 1931 (Box 3:68)
    - Anchor bridge 296 in Greenwich, Connecticut, looking west. Transformers are on the anchor bridge and a railroad car is on the track,May 1931 (Box 3:69)
    - Transformers at anchor bridge 296, located at interlocking tower Signal Station 28, east of Greenwich, Connecticut, station. This photo was taken in the same location as the previous photo (69),May 1931 (Box 3:70)
    - Transformers at anchor bridge 296 located at interlocking tower signal station 28 east of the Greenwich, Connecticut, station, May 1931 (Box 3:71)
    - Anchor bridge 310 in Cos Cob, Connecticut (power station) looking east. Transformers sit on the anchor bridge and connect to catenary wires. A signal station is on the right side of the track. This image was taken in the same location as the previous photo (71),May 1931 (Box 3:72)
    - Sound Beach, Connecticut, anchor bridge 345 looking east. Transformers sit on the anchor bridge and connect to catenaries,May 1931 (Box 3:73)
    - Stamford, Connecticut (New Canaan, Connecticut bridge) anchor bridge 374 looking west. Transformers sit on the anchor bridge and a signal station is on the left of the railroad tracks,April 1931 (Box 3:74)
    - Stamford, Connecticut (New Canaan, Connecticut bridge) anchor bridge 374 looking east. Transformers sit on an anchor bridge and connect to catenary wires. A signal station is on the right side of the railroad tracks. Three trains are visible in the background. One man is on the left side of the tracks. This image was taken in the same location as the previous photo (74),April 1931 (Box 3:75)
    - Interlocking tower Signal Station 40, in service, with Darien, Connecticut, freight house in background. Includes view of anchor bridge 465 looking west,April 1931 (Box 3:76)
    - Darien, Connecticut, anchor bridge 465 looking east. Signal station 10 is on the right of the railroad tracks. There is another railroad building with a platform on the left side of the railroad tracks. A railroad car is in the background. One man stands on the tracks and three men stand next to the signal station. This image was taken in the same location as the previous photo (76),April 1931 (Box 3:77)
    - South Norwalk, Connecticut (Danbury, Connecticut bridge) anchor bridge 524 looking west. Transformers sit on the anchor bridge and connect to catenary wires. A small railroad shed sits on the left side of the track near the anchor bridge,April 1931 (Box 3:78)
    - South Norwalk, Connecticut (Danbury, Connecticut bridge) anchor bridge 524 looking east. Transformers sit on the anchor bridge and connect to catenary wires. Non-railroad buildings crowd around both sides of the track. This image was taken in the same location as the previous photo (78). This image has been reversed in the print,April 1931 (Box 3:79)
    - Greens Farms, Connecticut 633 anchor bridge looking east. Transformers sit on top of the anchor bridge and connect to catenary wires. A signal station stands to the left of the tracks,May 1931 (Box 3:80)
    - Anchor bridge 736 by Burr Road in Bridgeport, Connecticut, looking east. Transformers sit on the anchor bridge and connect to catenary wires. A man stands on the tracks with a railroad car behind him,April 1931 (Box 3:81)
    - Anchor bridge 776 in Bridgeport, Connecticut, looking east. Shows Signal Station 62 "puzzle" switches at station. A caboose is in the center of the photo,April 1931 (Box 3:82)
    - Anchor bridge 803 in Bridgeport, Connecticut (Central Avenue) looking west. Transformers connected to catenary wires sit on the anchor bridge. Industrial buildings are visible in the background on both sides of the railroad tracks,April 1931 (Box 3:83)
    - Anchor bridge 803 in Bridgeport, Connecticut (Central Avenue)looking east. A motor vehicle bridge is behind the anchor bridge and crosses the expanse of the tracks. This image was taken in the same location as the previous photo (83),April 1931 (Box 3:84)
    - Anchor bridge 814 in Bridgeport, Connecticut (Bishop Avenue) looking west,April 1931 (Box 3:85)
    - Anchor bridge 814 in Bridgeport, Connecticut (Bishop Avenue) looking east. Transformers sit on the anchor bridge and connect to catenary wires. To the left of the railroad tracks is a signal station. This image was taken in the same location as the previous photo (85),April 1931 (Box 3:86)
    - Signal in Devon, Connecticut, looking east. A signal station stands to the left of the railroad tracks. Anchor bridge 864 is included,April 1931 (Box 3:87)
    - Anchor bridge 867 in Devon, Connecticut, looking east. In the distance a man is walking by the far left track,April 1931 (Box 3:88)
    - Catenary bridge 1080 displaying horn gap switches looking west in New Haven, Connecticut (Fair Street). The image focuses on the bridge from a height equal to the top portion of the bridge. The catenary wires can be seen in great detail,April 1931 (Box 3:89)
    - New Haven, Connecticut, anchor bridge 1104 (Mill River Junction) looking east. Catenary wires emerging from the top left corner of the photo connect to transformers on top of the anchor bridge. A signal station is on the right of the tracks,April 1931 (Box 3:90)
    - Ceder Hill, Connecticut, anchor bridge 1117 (near New Haven) looking west. A motor vehicle bridge crosses the railroad tracks just behind the anchor bridge. The tracks split into two different ground levels, the higher of which is on the right side of the photo. A fire seems to be burning on the higher section of the tracks and emenating smoke in the dirt to the left of the track,April 1931 (Box 3:91)